###@header@macseThis is the release 1.0.0.i5 of MACSE===================================MACSE includes a series of tools dedicated to multiple sequence alignment of (pseudo-)coding DNA sequences.MACSE is able to handle frameshifts and stop codons (either real or due to sequencing errors). It is thus especially adapted to align reads or EST together with more reliable sequences, or to align pseudo-genes together with functional genes.MACSE options thus allow to define two sets of sequences, the "reliable ones" and "the less reliable ones", and to provide different costs for frameshifts and stop codons in those two types of sequences.Warnings:=========Note that since the program is quite memory consuming you may have to add some extra memory to the java machine using the Xmx option "java -jar -Xmx600m macse_v1.0.0.jar ...".###@footer@macseFurther help:==================================To obtain detailed options of a program, simply call it without parameters, e.g.:java -jar macse_1.0.0.jar -prog alignSequences.As the alignment is guided by the amino-acid translation it is crucial to indicate the correct genetic code using its number (see MACSE main help for code numbers). You can provide a default genetic code for all sequences, or use a simple text file to indicate the genetic code of each sequence.Available genetic codes are those of the NCBI:=============================================1. The_Standard_Code2. The_Vertebrate_Mitochondrial_Code3. The_Yeast_Mitochondrial_Code4. The_Mold_Protozoan_and_Coelenterate_Mitochondrial_Code_and_the_Mycoplasma_Spiroplasma_Code 5. The_Invertebrate_Mitochondrial_Code6. The_Ciliate_Dasycladacean_and_Hexamita_Nuclear_Code9. The_Echinoderm_and_Flatworm_Mitochondrial_Code10. The_Euplotid_Nuclear_Code11. The_Bacterial_Archaeal_and_Plant_Plastid_Code12. The_Alternative_Yeast_Nuclear_Code13. The_Ascidian_Mitochondrial_Code14. The_Alternative_Flatworm_Mitochondrial_Code15. Blepharisma_Nuclear_Code16. Chlorophycean_Mitochondrial_Code21. Trematode_Mitochondrial_Code22. Scenedesmus_obliquus_mitochondrial_Code23. Thraustochytrium_Mitochondrial_Codefor details please see: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Taxonomy/Utils/wprintgc.cgiIf you find MACSE useful please cite:==================================MACSE : Multiple Alignment of Coding SEquences accounting for frameshifts and stop codons. Vincent Ranwez, Sebastien Harispe, Frederic Delsuc, and Emmanuel JP DouzeryPLoS ONE 6(9): e22594MACSE on the web================- [project and source code]: http://kimura.univ-montp2.fr:8080/projects/macse- [web service]: http://kimura.univ-montp2.fr:8080/projects/macse - [publication]: http://www.plosone.org/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0022594###@header@alignSequencesThis program aligns coding sequences by using their AA translation while allowing frameshifts and stop codons (either real or due to sequence errors). ###@footer@alignSequencesAdvised costs:=============By default, sequences are considered to be reliable coding sequences and the costs for frameshifts and stop codons are high (respectively 30 and 100).If you include reads or contigs from NGS, we advise to assign the corresponding sequences lower costs for frameshifts and stop codons (e.g. respectively 10 and 60, since it is frequent that NGS data contain an extra base or miss one).Similarly, if you include pseudogenes, we advise assigning to the corresponding sequences lower costs for frameshifts and stop codons (e.g. respectively 20 and 10, since they no longer undergo selective pressure a stop codon can rise from just a recent mutation).###@header@alignTwoProfilesThis program aligns two precomputed alignments without questioning them. In this case, it can be worth using the refineAlignment program to improve the resulting alignment.###@footer@alignTwoProfilesAdvised costs:=============By default, sequences are considered to be reliable coding sequences and the costs for frameshifts and stop codons are high (respectively 30 and 100).If you include reads or contigs from NGS, we advise assigning to the corresponding sequences lower costs for frameshifts and stop codons (e.g. respectively 10 and 60, since it is frequent that NGS data contain an extra base or miss one).Similarly, if you include pseudogenes we advise assigning to the corresponding sequences lower costs for frameshifts and stop codons (e.g. respectively 20 and 10, since they no longer undergo selective pressure a stop codon can arise from just a recent mutation).As the alignment is guided by the amino-acid translation it is crucial to indicate the correct genetic code using its number (see MACSE main help for code numbers). You can provide a default genetic code for all sequences, or use a simple text file to indicate the genetic code of each sequence.###@header@enrichAlignmentThis program iteratively adds sequences to the original alignment, you can use parameters to avoid adding sequences containing too much frameshifts or stop codons. In this case, it can be worth using the refineAlignment program to improve the resulting alignment.###@header@exportAlignmentThis program allows to get rid of "!" symbols in the nucleotidic alignment. You can chose to replace a "!" symbol by a "-" or "N" or to ignore the whole codon containing the "!", replacing it by either "---" or "NNN". The translated alignment can still contain some "!" but this is not a big deal since, unlike for codon, a simple "search/replace" allows to handle them.###@header@reportGapsAA2NTThis program allows to report gaps observed in an AA alignment on NT sequences to produce a NT alignment. The genetic code is used to handle the stop codon that could be present in NT sequence but missing in AA sequences. A warning is printed when the two files do not contain exactly the same sequence identifiers, only sequences present in both files will be present in the output.Note that if a NT sequence contain a partial final codon the corresponding nucleotide are ignored. If the final codon is a stop codon but the AA sequence do not contain a *, the corresponding codon is also ignored to ensure the alignment consistency (i.e. identical length of all aligned NT sequences) ###@header@splitAlignmentThis program allows to split an alignment, you can isolate a subset of sequences and/or a subset of sites.###@header@refineAlignmentThis program allows to refine an alignment produced, for instance, by "enrichAlignment" or "alignTwoProfiles" subprograms of MACSE. This program also provides an efficient solution to test alternative costs (much faster than re-aligning sequences from scratch with different costs). The refinement of a an alignment is done by splitting it in two subAlignments and realigning them afterward. The splits are done based on a guided tree used to build the multiple sequence alignment, each of its branch define a partition of the sequences that can be used to split the alignment (as done with spliAlignment). You can either test only split related to terminal branches (remove and re-aligning each sequence one after the other) or test splits defined by all branches (better but much longer).